Finding Aid for the Paul Hartman papers, 1935-1965 LSC.1456
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Hartman papers
1935-1965
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hartman, Paul
LSC.1456
4.0 Linear Feet 8 boxes
12 oversize_boxes
Paul Hartman (1910-1973) was born in San Francisco, California. He was a dancer, actor, magician and singer appearing in vaudeville, the theater, film and television. The collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, diaries, clippings, programs, sheet music, books, pamphlets, and memorabilia of Paul Hartman and family members.
Restrictions on Access
Stored off-site. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frances Hartman, 1976.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917203903606533
Biography
Paul Hartman was born in 1910 in San Francisco, California; studied dancing with his aunt, Flora Norris; made stage debut at age of six weeks at the Tivoli Opera House, San Francisco, and first speaking role in the same theater in Johnny Comes Marching Home (1912); graduated from University of California at Berkeley; became dancer, actor, magician and singer; married dancer, actress, and singer Grace Barrett; they appeared in vaudeville in the act, Hartman and Barrett, and toured the Far East, Europe and the United States; in New York, they played at the Empire Room of the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel and the Plaza Hotel, and appeared at the Dorchester in London; Paul Hartman made his Broadway debut in Ballyhoo of 1932, going on to play Alexander Throttlebottom in Of thee I Sing (1952), Cap'n Andy in Show Boat (1956), and Hines in The Pajama Game (1957); appeared in five films, including Inherit the Wind (1960); appeared in television programs, including The Hartmans at Home, The Twilight Zone, Have Gun Will Travel, The Lucy Show, The Ed Sullivan Show, and I've Got a Secret; received the Lambs Award for his contribution to the American theater (1958); he died on October 2, 1973.
Scope and Content
Collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, diaries, clippings, programs, sheet music, books, pamphlets, and memorabilia of dancer, actor, magician and singer Paul Hartman. Materials also relate to his wife, dancer, actress and singer Grace Barrett Hartman; their son Ted Hartman, a sketch writer; and Paul's father, Ferris Hartman, owner and director of Ferris Hartman Comic Opera Company.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Photograph albums (Boxes 1,3,6-7,9).
Dance descriptions notebook (Box 1).
Magic and illusion: the Tarbell system (Box 2).
Scrapbooks (Boxes 3,10-17).
Correspondence (Boxes 4,7).
Diaries (Box 5).
Memorabilia (Boxes 7-8).
Contracts (Box 8).
Sheet music (Boxes 8,19-20).
Phonograph records (Box 9).
Programs and magazines featuring the Hartmans (Box 18).
Diaries.; Actors -- United States -- Archives; Photograph albums.; Scrapbooks.; Hartman, Ferris--Archives.; Hartman, Grace, 1907-1955--Archives.; Hartman, Paul, 1904-1973--Archives.; Hartman, Ted--Archives.; Hartman family; Hartman, Ferris; Hartman, Grace; Hartman, Ted; Hartman family--Archives.
- Photograph albums, scrapbook, dance descriptions notebook., ca. 1906-1922; 1935-1936 (Box 1)
- Tarbell system Magic copyright, 1927. (Box 2)
- Scrapbook, diary, photograph album, and correspondence, 1922-1929; n.d.; ca. 1952; ca. 1944. (Box 3)
- Correspondence, personal papers and diaries. (Box 4)
- Diaries. (Box 5)
- Photograph albums, ca., 1925-1930. (Box 6)
- Correspondence, photographs, memorabilia. (Box 7)
- Contracts, sheet music, memorabilia. (Box 8)
- Photograph album, ca. phonograph records., 1915-1970 (Box 9)
- Scrapbook,, loose photographs ca., 1938-1943 1935-1965. (Box 10)
- Scrapbook, ca., 1951-1956. (Box 11)
- Scrapbooks, 1938, 1949-1950. (Box 12)
- Scrapbooks, and, 1939-1941 1947-1948. (Box 13)
- Scrapbook, 1960 -1971. (Box 14)
- Scrapbook, Stage magazine, 1927-1935. 1936-1938. (Box 15)
- Scrapbooks, and, 1930-1938 1940-1942. (Box 16)
- Scrapbooks, and, 1939-1950 1942-1944. (Box 17)
- Programs and magazines featuring the Hartmans. (Box 18)
- Sheet music for the Hartmans' vaudeville and nightclub acts. (Box 19, Box 20)